<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Nik Dot Codes</title>
 <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/"/>
 <updated>2023-10-25T13:18:27+00:00</updated>
 <id>http://0.0.0.0:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Nik</name>
   <email>hi@nik.codes</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Getting this old school world built</title>
   <link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2023/10/25/gygax-75-start/"/>
   <updated>2023-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2023/10/25/gygax-75-start</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, I have a weekly TTRPG group in the next town along where we do stints of 12&lt;em&gt;(ish)&lt;/em&gt; weeks of whatever game people want to play. We’ve had a bit of everything;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;D&amp;amp;D&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pathfinder&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shadowrun&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Traveller&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mork Borg&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Troika&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The list goes on…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the next rounds of games isn’t until January time, which gives me a great opportunity to do what I’ve been wanting to do for a while&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Run my own OSE campaign!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve ran a few games now (mainly Mork Borg &amp;amp; Troika) but these were simply adventures that I’ve obtained over time with not much in between; which was fun and all, but I don’t feel really scratched that itch that I have deep down. So before the next series of games, I’ve decided to come up with a campaign setting, and I plan on using OSE to run it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-the-hell-is-ose&quot;&gt;What the hell is OSE&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://necroticgnome.com/&quot;&gt;OSE (or Old School Essentials)&lt;/a&gt; is a tidy up of the Basic &amp;amp; Expert Editions of Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons (B/X) from back when in the 80’s. It’s a step away from the “Powerful to Superhero quest to save the land” that 5&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; edition has led to and is more of “Layman to Stronger &amp;amp; Richer Layman”; one of the key features of these older style games is an emphasis on the world over the party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year I backed a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/exaltedfuneral/old-school-essentials-fantasy-rpg-box-sets&quot;&gt;Kickstarter from Exhaulted Funeral&lt;/a&gt; and I got so many wonderful books earlier this year, and it’s just been sitting on my shelf gathering dust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/jpg/blog/20231025/OSECollection.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My OSE Collection.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;My OSE Collection.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside this, I have amassed a number of different adventures, modules, and other bits and pieces into a nice collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-what-do-you-need-to-do&quot;&gt;So what do you need to do?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I’ve got all of this stuff, then what actual work do I need to put in?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned, there is importance in the world. General idea is to drop the party in a location, and let them decide where to go. As the GM, it’s my job to build a satisfying world with enough life and intrigue to keep the players wanting to play. These can be…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Locations (Map, Towns, Cities, Places of Interest, etc…)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Factions (Countries/Fiefdoms, Religions, Guilds, etc…)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;History &amp;amp; Lore&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I am aiming for is creating a world where, in a 12 week period, a party can play their own adventure - the world can change (alliances can change, powers grow or wane, etc…) - but there’s nothing stopping or impeding another party from being able to have their own adventure in another corner of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;sounds-like-a-lot-of-work&quot;&gt;Sounds like a lot of work&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in a relatively short amount of time too. Thankfully, for a game to start, we don’t need the whole map planned out fully. Just like many video games out there, we have a starting location with limited access to the wider world out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there’s many tools out there to help, in particular I’ll be starting with &lt;a href=&quot;https://ia802600.us.archive.org/7/items/the-gygax-75-challenge-ttrpg-worldbuilding-resource/gygax75v3.2.pdf&quot;&gt;the Gygax 75 Challenge&lt;/a&gt;. This 5 week process was recommended by many of the internets and is a nice framework to getting started. Then I can start slipping in elements from my module &amp;amp; adventure collection, and building out the world more and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or at least that’s the plan anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s the plan, every week I’ll post up the results of that week’s work according to the book &amp;amp; hopefully by the start of December, I should have a nicely populated world, ready for adventuring in!.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until next time!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
